<h1> Recent publications</h1> 
(updated May 18th, 2014)

<article>
    <header>
        <h3 class="title">Direct phase-sensitive identification of a d-form factor density wave in underdoped cuprates</h3>
    </header>
    <div id="authorlist">K. Fujita, M. H. Hamidian, S. D. Edkins, C. K. Kim, Y. Kohsaka, M. Azuma, M. Takano, H. Takagi, H. Eisaki, S.-I. Uchida, A. Allias, M. J. Lawler, E.-A. Km, S. Sachdev and J. C. S. Davis</div>
    <p> High-temperature superconductivity emerges when holes are introduced
        into the antiferromagnetic, insulating CuO2 plane of the cuprates.
        Intervening between the insulator and the superconductor is the
        mysterious pseudogap phase. Evidence has been accumulating that
        this phase supports an exotic density wave state that may be key
        to its existence. By introducing visualization techniques that
        discriminate the electronic structure at the two oxygen sites
        with each CuO2 unit cell, we demonstrate that this density wave
        consists of periodic modulations maintaining a phase difference
        of π between every such pair of oxygen sites. Therefore, the
        cuprate pseudogap phase contains a previously unknown electronic
        state—a density wave with a d-symmetry form factor.</p>
    <footer>
        <p>Read more on <a  class="more" href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1404.0362">
        arXiv.org</a>,
        <a class="more" href="http://www.pnas.org/content/early/2014/07/02/1406297111.short">
        Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci., USA, 10.1073/pnas.1406297111</a>.</p>
    </footer>
</article>
<article>
    <header>
        <h3 class="title">Simultaneous Transitions in Cuprate Momentum-Space Topology and Electronic Symmetry Breaking</h3>
    </header>
    <div id="authorlist">K. Fujita, Chung Koo Kim, Inhee Lee, Jinho Lee, M. H. Hamidian, I. A. Firmo, S. Mukhopadhyay, H. Eisaki, S. Uchida, M. J. Lawler, E.-A. Kim and J. C. Davis</div>
    <p> The existence of electronic symmetry breaking in the underdoped
        cuprates and its disappearance with increased hole density p are
        now widely reported. However, the relation between this transition
        and the momentum-space $\vec k$-space electronic structure
        underpinning the superconductivity has not yet been established.
        Here, we visualize the $\vec Q=0$ (intra–unit-cell) and
        $\vec Q\neq 0$ (density-wave) broken-symmetry states,
        simultaneously with the coherent $\vec k$-space topology, for
        Bi2Sr2CaCu2O8+δ samples spanning the phase diagram 0.06 ≤ p ≤ 0.23.
        We show that the electronic symmetry-breaking tendencies weaken
        with increasing p and disappear close to a critical doping pc = 0.19.
        Concomitantly, the coherent $\vec k$-space topology undergoes an
        abrupt transition, from arcs to closed contours, at the same pc.
        These data reveal that the $\vec k$-space topology transformation
        in cuprates is linked intimately with the disappearance of the
        electronic symmetry breaking at a concealed critical point.</p>
    <footer>
        <p>Read more on <a  class="more" href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1210.1585">
        arXiv.org</a>,
        <a class="more" href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/344/6184/612.abstract?sid=0a15f266-602f-4798-84be-d628cee38862">
        Science <b>344</b>, 612 (2014)</a>.</p>
    </footer>
</article>
<article>
    <header>
        <h3 class="title">Striped spin liquid crystal ground state
            instability of kagome antiferromagnets </h3>
    </header>
    <div id="authorlist">B. K. Clark, J. M. Kinder, Eric Neuscamman,
    G. K.-L. Chan, and M. J. Lawler</div>
    <p>
    The Dirac spin liquid ground state of the spin 1/2 Heisenberg kagome
    antiferromagnet has potential instabilities. This has been suggested
    as the reason why it does not emerge as the ground state in large-scale
    numerical calculations. However, previous attempts to observe these
    instabilities have failed. We report on the discovery of a projected
    BCS state with lower energy than the projected Dirac spin liquid state
    which provides new insight into the stability of the ground state of the
    kagome antiferromagnet. The new state has three remarkable features. First,
    it breaks spatial symmetry in an unusual way that may leave spinons
    deconfined along one direction. Second, it breaks the U(1) gauge symmetry
    down to Z2. Third, it has the spatial symmetry of a previously proposed
    “monopole” suggesting that it is an instability of the Dirac spin liquid.
    The state described herein also shares a remarkable similarity to the
    distortion of the kagome lattice observed at low Zn concentrations in
    Zn-paratacamite and in recently grown single crystals of volborthite
    suggesting it may already be realized in these materials.</p>
    <footer>
        <p>Read more on <a  class="more" href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1210.1585">
        arXiv.org</a>,
        <a class="more" href="http://prl.aps.org/abstract/PRL/v111/i18/e187205">
        Phys. Rev. Lett. <b>111</b>, 187205 (2013)</a>.</p>
    </footer>
</article>
<article>
    <header>
        <h3 class="title">Emergent gauge dynamics of highly frustrated
            magnets</h3>
    </header>
    <div id="authorlist">M. J. Lawler</div>
    <p>
    Condensed matter exhibits a wide variety of exotic emergent phenomena
    such as the fractional quantum Hall effect and the low temperature
    cooperative behavior of highly frustrated magnets. I consider the classical
    Hamiltonian dynamics of spins of the latter phenomena using a method
    introduced by Dirac in the 1950s by assuming they are constrained to their
    lowest energy configurations as a simplifying measure. Focusing on the
    kagome antiferromagnet as an example, I find it is a gauge system with
    topological dynamics and non-locally connected edge states for certain
    open boundary conditions similar to doubled Chern–Simons electrodynamics
    expected of a Z2 spin liquid. These dynamics are also similar to electrons
    in the fractional quantum Hall effect. The classical theory presented here
    is a first step toward a controlled semi-classical description of the spin
    liquid phases of many pyrochlore and kagome antiferromagnets and toward a
    description of the low energy classical dynamics of the corresponding
    unconstrained Heisenberg models.</p>
    <footer>
        <p>Read more on: <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1104.0721">
        arXiv.org</a>,
        <a href="http://iopscience.iop.org/1367-2630/15/4/043043">
        New J. Phys. <b>15</b>, 043043 (2013)</a>.</p>
    </footer>
</article>
<article>
    <header>
        <h3 class="title">Topological Defects Coupling Smectic Modulations
        to Intra–Unit-Cell Nematicity in Cuprates</h3>
    </header>
    <div id="authorlist">A. Mesaros, K. Fujita, H. Eisaki, S. Uchida,
    J. C. Davis, S. Sachdev, J. Zaanen, M. J. Lawler, Eun-Ah Kim</div>
    <p>
    We study the coexisting smectic modulations and intra–unit-cell nematicity
    in the pseudogap states of underdoped Bi2Sr2CaCu2O8+δ. By visualizing their
    spatial components separately, we identified 2π topological defects throughout
    the phase-fluctuating smectic states. Imaging the locations of large numbers
    of these topological defects simultaneously with the fluctuations in the
    intra–unit-cell nematicity revealed strong empirical evidence for a coupling
    between them. From these observations, we propose a Ginzburg-Landau functional
    describing this coupling and demonstrate how it can explain the coexistence
    of the smectic and intra–unit-cell broken symmetries and also correctly predict
    their interplay at the atomic scale. This theoretical perspective can lead to
    unraveling the complexities of the phase diagram of cuprate
    high-critical-temperature superconductors.</p>
    <footer>
        <p>Read more on <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1108.0487">
        arXiv.org</a>,
        <a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/333/6041/426.short" class="more">
        Science 333, <b>426</b> (2011)</a>.</p>
    </footer>
</article>
